Guide to the North Carolina Temple and Synagogue historical collection, 1926-2010 and undated RL.11012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
North Carolina Temple and Synagogue historical records collection
1926-2010 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina
RL.11012
6.8 Linear Feet 9 boxes; 1 oversize folder
The North Carolina Temple and Synagogue Historical Collection is an artificial collection created from materials donated to the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina that are from or related to Jewish congregations across North Carolina. There are administrative records for some of the temples and synagogues represented, including Temple Beth El (Weldon, Halifax Co., NC), Temple Israel (Kinston, Lenoir Co., NC), Temple Beth El (Lumberton, Robeson Co., NC), and Temple Oheb Sholom (Goldsboro, Wayne Co., NC), of which Gertrude Weil was a member. Also present are materials related to Rabbi Jerome G. Tolochko's service as chaplain to Marine Corps bases in North Carolina during and after World War II. Central themes include congregational and community events, building dedications, anniversaries, religious services, membership, religious education, and Sisterhood, Brotherhood, and Hadassah activities. Types of material include correspondence, bulletins, programs, organizational scrapbooks, directories, teaching materials, financial ledgers, clippings, and photographs.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Collection Overview
The North Carolina Temple and Synagogue Historical Collection is an artificial collection created from materials donated to the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina that are from or related to Jewish congregations across North Carolina. There are administrative records for some of the temples and synagogues represented, including Temple Beth El (Weldon, Halifax Co., NC), Temple Israel (Kinston, Lenoir Co., NC), Temple Beth El (Lumberton, Robeson Co., NC), and Temple Oheb Sholom (Goldsboro, Wayne Co., NC), of which Gertrude Weil was a member. Also present are materials related to Rabbi Jerome G. Tolochko's service as chaplain to Marine Corps bases in North Carolina during and after World War II.
Major topics of the collection include congregational and community events, building dedications, anniversaries, religious services, membership, adult and youth religious education, and Sisterhood, Brotherhood, and Hadassah activities. Types of material include bulletins, pamphlets, event programs, organizational scrapbooks, directories, teaching materials, financial ledgers, correspondence, clippings, and photographs.
Arrangement
Materials are grouped according to congregation, then arranged chronologically.
Related Material
Beth-El Synagogue records, 1899-1988 (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina records, 1750-2014 and undated (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
Historical Note
The Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina (JHFNC) is an independent organization dedicated to preserving and presenting the history of the Jewish people of North Carolina. Through public programming and exhibits, the JHFNC aspires to educate and showcase the richness of Jewish Life as well as promote a familiarity with the culture and lifestyle of Jews to the general public. In 2014, the JHFNC transferred their historical collections, including the materials in the North Carolina Temple and Synagogue Historical Collection, to the Rubenstein Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials in the North Carolina Temple and Synagogue Historical Collection were received as a gift in June 2014 by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, as part of the Jewish Heritage Foundation of North Carolina Collection.
Judaism -- North Carolina; Rabbis -- North Carolina; Military chaplains -- United States.; Jews -- North Carolina -- Social life and customs; Synagogues -- North Carolina; Jewish religious education of children -- North Carolina; Synagogue dedication services -- North Carolina; Beth-El Synagogue (Durham, N.C.); Temple Oheb Sholom (Goldsboro, N.C.); Weil, Gertrude; Temple Beth El (Lumberton, N.C.); Hadassah, the Women's Zionist Organization of America; Tolochko, Jerome G.; Temple Israel (Kinston, N.C.); Temple Emanu-El (Weldon, N.C.)
- Goldsboro, NC - Temple Oheb Sholom, 1941-1962; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Materials include membership rolls, financial documents, meeting minutes, and other congregational records, as well as a commemorative World War II scroll. Sisterhood and regional Hadassah records include minutes from meetings in which Gertrude Weil participated.
  Some materials related to Temple Oheb Sholom during the tenure of Rabbi Jerome G. Tolochko are also found in the Kinston, NC - Temple Israel series.
  Biographical / Historical
  Oheb Sholom is a Reform congregation founded in Goldsboro, NC, in 1883. Its past membership included suffragist and activist Gertrude Weil (1879-1971), who was a member of the temple's Sisterhood and leader of the local and regional Hadassah chapters.
  - Congregational records, 1941-1962; 1 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Congregational records, 1941-1962; 2 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Congregational records, 1941-1962; 3 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Congregational records, 1941-1962; 4 of 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - V-E Day scroll, 1945 (Box 9)
  - [Temple Oheb Sholom Sisterhood meeting minutes], 1954-1960; 1 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Temple Oheb Sholom Sisterhood meeting minutes], 1954-1960; 2 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Temple Oheb Sholom Sisterhood meeting minutes], 1954-1960; 3 of 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Seaboard Region of Hadassah, Goldsboro, NC records], 1954-1956; 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [Seaboard Region of Hadassah, Goldsboro, NC records], 1954-1956; 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Seaboard Region of Hadassah, Goldsboro, NC account book], 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Kinston, NC - Temple Israel, 1940-1985 and undated; 2
  Materials in the Kinston, NC - Temple Israel series include bulletins, scrapbooks, hymnals, Hagaddot, educational materials, scripts for television and radio programs and children's performances, and plans for the construction of the 1955 temple. Also included are photocopies of materials related to Rabbi J. G. Tolochko's military chaplaincies during and after World War II. Scattered photocopies of bulletins from Temple Oheb Sholom (Goldsboro, NC), where Tolochko served prior to Temple Israel, are present in the military chaplaincy materials.
  The Orthodox congregation of Tipereth Israel was founded in Kinston, Lenoir County, NC, in 1903. In 1949, the synagogue was renamedTemple Israel, and it officially became a Reform congregation in 1952.
  Rabbi Jerome G. Tolochko, formerly of Temple Oheb Sholom (Goldsboro, NC), served the Temple Israel congregation from 1946 to 1969. He also served as chaplain for the Marine Corps bases at Camp Lejeune and Cherry Point, NC.
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volume 1, 1946, September-1947, May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volumes 2-3, 1947, September-1949, June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volume 4, 1949, September-1950, May (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volume 5, 1950, September-1951, June (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volume 6, 1951, September-1952, June (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volumes 7-8, 1952, September-1954, June (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volume 9, 1954, September-1955, May (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volume 10, 1955, September-1956, May (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volumes 11-12, 1956, September-1958, May (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, volumes 13-14, 1958, August-1960, May (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, Kinston, NC, volumes 15-16, 1960, September-1962, August (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, Kinston, NC, volumes 17-18, 1962, September-1964, May (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, Kinston, NC, volume 19, 1964, August-1965, May (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, Kinston, NC, volume 20, 1965, August-1966, May (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, Kinston, NC, volume 21, 1966, August-1967, May (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, Kinston, NC, volume 22, 1967, August-1968, May (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, Kinston, NC, volume 23, 1968, August-1969, June (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Temple Israel Messenger, Kinston, NC, volume 24, 1969, August-1970, May (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sunday school projects, circa 1940s-1960s; 1 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sunday school projects, circa 1940s-1960s; 2 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sunday school projects, circa 1940s-1960s; 3 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sunday school lessons, circa 1940s-1960s; 1 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Sunday school lessons, circa 1940s-1960s; 2 of 2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes copy of "Hebrew for Beginners" by Rabbi Jerome G. Tolochko, copyright 1953.
  - Materials related to various programs, 1910, 1932, 1939-1969, undated; 1 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Materials related to various programs, 1910, 1932, 1939-1969, undated; 2 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Materials related to various programs, 1910, 1932, 1939-1969, and undated; 3 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Printed materials, 1949-1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Printed materials, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Printed materials, 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Printed materials, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Printed materials, 1968, 1985, and undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Printed materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Temple Israel, Kinston, NC, Book of Remembrance, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook of community, religious, and educational programming, circa 1940s-1960s; 1 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook of community, religious, and educational programming, circa 1940s-1960s; 2 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook of community, religious, and educational programming, circa 1940s-1960s; 3 of 3 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Television programs, confirmation programs, sheet music, 1954-1968 and undated; 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Television programs, confirmation programs, sheet music, 1954-1968 and undated; 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook on new temple dedication (1955) and tenth anniversary (1965), 1954-1955, 1965; 1 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook on new temple dedication (1955) and tenth anniversary (1965), 1954-1955, 1966; 2 of 2 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Temple Israel archives - Temple seating plans, drawings for interior and exterior objects, circa 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Temple architectural plans, circa 1954-1955 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - “200 years of progress: a report of the history and achievements of the people of Lenoir County”, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Correspondence, bulletins, reports, and other materials related to Tolochko's chaplaincies at Cherry Point and Camp Lejeune military bases
  - Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, circa 1942-1947 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1947, July-December (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1948, January-February (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1948, April-August (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1948, September-October (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1948, November-1949, January (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1949, February-October (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1949, November-1951, February (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - [Temple Israel, Kinston, NC] Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1951, July-1957, December (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - [Temple Israel, Kinston, NC] Rabbi J. G. Tolochko military chaplaincy materials, 1961, August-1969, January and undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Lumberton, NC - Temple Beth El, 1963-1988; 3
  Historical note
  Temple Beth El closed in 1998.
  The Lumberton, NC - Temple Beth El series includes meeting minutes of the temple and its Sisterhood, financial ledgers, news articles, and administrative records.
  - Financial ledger, 1971-1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Meeting minutes, 1965-1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Sisterhood Temple Beth El, 1966, 1969, 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Administrative records, 1963-1991 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Clippings and articles, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Financial ledger, 1964-1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Financial ledger, 1967-1988; 1 of 4 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Financial ledger, 1967-1988; 2 of 4 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Financial ledger, 1967-1988; 3 of 4 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Financial ledger, 1967-1988; 4 of 4 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Weldon, NC - Temple Emanu-El, 1926-2005 and undated; 4
  Materials related to the history of Temple Emanu-el from the construction and dedication of the temple in 1954 to its dissolution in the early 2000s. Materials document the daily operations of the temple including programs for various services, budgeting and reporting, and the minutes for committee and congregational meetings. Materials also document the activities of the Weldon congregation (including the Sisterhood Temple Emanu-el), its religious leaders, its participation in the Circuit Riding Rabbi Project, and the temple’s importance in the Weldon community and beyond.
  Materials include correspondence, programs, newspaper clippings, blueprints, newsletters, telegrams, and photographs.
  - [Closing Exercises Weldon Sabbath School], 1926 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - [Weldon postcards], 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Meeting minutes, 1948-1955; 1 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Meeting minutes, 1948-1955; 2 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - [Photographs - Temple Emanu-El, 1948-2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Temple Emanu-El Dedication, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Temple Emanu-El building, 1954-1956 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Temple Emanu-El membership, 1954-1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Circuit Riding, 1954-1961, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Temple Emanu-El correspondence, 1954-1962, 1969-1973; 1 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Temple Emanu-El correspondence, 1954-1962, 1969-1973; 2 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Temple Emanu-El Interfaith/Thanksgiving, 1954-2000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Temple Emanu-El Religious Committee, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Confirmation exercises (programs), 1955, 1960, 1963, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Temple Emanu-El - NCAJWM, 1955, 1967-1971 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Temple Emanu-El History, 1955, 1997, 2005 and undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Temple Emanu-El Piano, 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Temple Emanu-El Anniversaries, 1955-1967; 1 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Temple Emanu-El Anniversaries, 1955-1967; 2 of 2 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Temple Emanu-El budget, 1955-1986 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Photographs - Temple Emanu-El Scrapbook, 1955-1999 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Temple Emanu-El Holidays, 1955-1999 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Temple Emanu-El - minutes, 1956-1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Temple Emanu-El newsletters, 1957-1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Meeting minutes, 1959-1970 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Temple Emanu-El Accessions, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Temple Emanu-El bulletins, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - [Programs for various services at Temple Emanu-El], 1967-1989 and undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Sisterhood Temple Emanu-El, 1970-1984 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Meeting minutes, 1999-2003 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Temple Emanu-El Soviet Jewry, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - [The Ten Commandments commentary and interpretation], undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Temple Emanu-El Bylaws and Standards, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Temple Emanu-El Certificates, 1955-1999 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Other temples and synagogues, 1952-2010; 5
  This series mainly consists of bulletins and other printed materials from various congregations, including programs from temple dedications, anniversaries, religious ceremonies, holiday observances, and other events.
  - Concord, NC - Havurat Olam - Bar Mitzvah program, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 1958-1972, 1980-1989, February (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 1989, March-December (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 1992-1993, May (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 1993, June-1996, May (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 1996, June-1997, March (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 1997, April-1999, February (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 2000, April-December (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 2001, January-March (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Bulletin, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El membership directories, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Durham, NC - Beth El Synagogue miscellaneous materials, 1929,1961, 1988-1993, 2001-2010 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Durham, NC - Judea Reform Congregation miscellaneous materials, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Durham, NC - Judea Reform Today (Temple bulletins), 1986, December, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Durham, NC - Judea Reform Today (Temple bulletins), 1991-1992, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Durham, NC - Judea Reform Today (Temple bulletins), 1996 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Durham, NC - Judea Reform Today (Temple bulletins), 1997-1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Greensboro, NC - Temple Emanuel bulletins, correspondence, 1962-1967, 1982-2007 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Greensboro, NC - Temple Emanuel 75th Anniversary program, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Greensboro, NC - Temple Emanuel Dedication Program, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Greensboro, NC - "Temple Emanuel Greensboro, 1907-2007: One Hundred Years of a Unique Jewish Experience in the South" (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Greensboro, NC - Temple Emanuel newspaper clippings, 1978-2008; 1 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Greensboro, NC - Temple Emanuel newspaper clippings, 1978-2008; 2 of 2 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Hendersonville, NC - Agudas Israel Congregation 87th Anniversary Celebration program, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - High Point, NC - High Point Hebrew Congregation Educational Center dedication program, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - High Point, NC - High Point Hebrew Congregation synagogue dedication program, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Wilson, NC - Temple Beth El - Dedication Journal, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Winston-Salem, NC - Temple Emanuel Fiftieth Anniversary [program], 1982 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Winston-Salem, NC - Temple Emanuel Book of Dedication, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Winston- Salem, NC - Temple Emanuel dedication book, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Winston-Salem, NC - Temple Emanuel, 75 Years [anniversary program], 2009 (Box 8, Folder 7)